A Guide to the Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, 1881-1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 September 5, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of September 4, and its enclosure from Mr. Burke. Wilson writes that it is always a comfort to hear from Dabney and hopes that what he is doing is meeting with Dabney's approval. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 November 20, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter regarding Col. Lincoln Karmany. Wilson says he is following strict professional standards in all promotions. He thinks the Mexican situation is slowly working itself out. Wilson says the Mexican situation and the currency situation are playing havoc with his golf game but that someday when his nerves are in shape he will challenge Dabney to golf. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has written on it "About golf" in pencil.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 November 25, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 1)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter about Mr. Burke regarding the postmaster position in Bedford City. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1913 December 10, Telegram (Box 1)
  Wilson invites Dabney to dinner on Thursday at 7 p.m.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1914 January 19, TLS 4 p. with envelope and enclosure (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of the 13th and responds to an inquiry about placing a regional reserve bank in Richmond. Wilson returns a telegram from Charles Pinckney on the same subject that Dabney had forwarded with his letter. The telegram is 3 pages and dated January 13, 1914, 3.24 p.m. Wilson also mentions receiving an article from Dabney, but does not elaborate on its contents. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1914 February 20, Western Union Telegram and envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson invites Dabney to lunch on "Saturday at one o'clock."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1914 March 20, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges with thanks Dabney's letter of the 18th regarding Hampson Gary for a post in Persia. Wilson also sends a thank-you from his daughter, Eleanor, regarding Dabney's kind words on Eleanor's engagement. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1914 April 27, TLS 4 p. with envelope and 1 unidentified tree leaf (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of the 23rd and mentions he will call Dabney's information about "Taylor" to the attention of the Secretary of the Navy.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1914 August 20, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of August 7. The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1915 January 4, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's New Year's letter and reciprocates Dabney's good wishes. Wilson mentions that he is interested in what Dabney has to say about Mr. Raleigh Minor's work. Wilson says that he must remain aloof about it for fear of seeming to "press the matter." Wilson tells Dabney that he will write Mr. Minor. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1915 February 13, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of February 12. Wilson states that he is already aware of the article to which Dabney had referred in his letter and is appreciative of Dabney's kindness. The typed closing reads "Affectionately your," and is signed "Woodrow Wilson"
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney May 14, 1915, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for the "fine letter" he wrote May 11. Wilson says he wishes he had more time to send an adequate answer. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1915 October 13, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of October 8 and of the happiness that has now come to him [his engagement to Edith Bolling Galt]. Wilson states that he hopes that it will soon be possible for Mrs. Galt to know Dabney as the "delightful" friend he is. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1916 January 13, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of January 10 concerning Mr. [John] Powell. Wilson says they were considering having him at the White House, but the musical "programme" already had been made. He and Mrs. Wilson send good wishes for the New Year. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1916 April 26, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of April 23. Wilson writes that he is full of gratitude and affection that Dabney should feel as he does about what Wilson is doing. Wilson says that these are times that try men's souls and that he hopes fire will purify the whole nation. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1916 May 10, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson regrets that he will not get to see Dabney, but that he is going "down the river" to get away for needed rest. Wilson writes that he is not "very keen" for any public dinner. Wilson writes a reference to a German note, but gives no indication what it was about. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1916 August 5, TLS 4 p. with envelope, (with enclosures: TLS 4 p. from the Postmaster General) (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) from the U.S.S. Mayflower to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson has sent Dabney's letter regarding the Brook Hill post office to the Postmaster General and encloses the Postmaster General's response. The Postmaster General writes that at the "instance" of Virginia Senators, the Governor of Virginia and a Virginia Representative, any change to the mail service has been postponed. He will look in to the taking the best action for the Brook Hill post office.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1916 November 23, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson expresses pleasure in the message Dabney sent. The typed closing reads "Cordially and sincerely yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1916 November 27, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of the 23rd and says that it "warmed the cockles of my heart." Wilson states he is "submerged" in messages from "many quarters." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 January 10, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges receipt of a letter regarding a Mr. Jenkins. Wilson says it will not be possible to excuse an individual guardsman and that "they" will probably not be much longer detained at the border. Wilson will send Dabney's and Jenkins' letter on to the Secretary of War. The typed closing reads "Cordially and faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." "Confidential" is typed at the top.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 January 10, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of the 7th regarding Hampson Gary. The letter reached him too late to consider Gary for the Third Assistant Secretary of State, but Wilson will forward the letter to the Secretary of State in the case that there might be other positions available. Wilson tells Dabney that he need not apologize for writing and says that it is a joy to hear from his old friends. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- J. P. Tumulty, Secretary to President Wilson, to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 January 13, TLS 4 p. and enclosure (TLS 1 p. carbon to President Wilson from Newton Baker, War Department) (Box 2)
  Tumulty (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Tumulty acknowledges Dabney's previous letter to the President regarding John B. Jenkins, Jr. The War Department has written President Wilson regarding the matter and a copy of the War Department letter is enclosed. The War Department letter acknowledges a discharge of Mr. Jenkins. The letter from the War Department has the stamped signature of Newton D. Baker.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 March 22, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that only illness has prevented him from acknowledging sooner Dabney's letter of March 3 and its enclosure, which brought him gratification. Wilson says it is delightful to have backing from such people. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 April 3, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that his address to Congress the previous evening was a response of a sort to Dabney's letter, although Wilson had not read it until that morning. Wilson appreciates what Dabney has sent him. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 12 April 1917, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of the 10th. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 13 April 1917, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes in regard to John Thompson Brown and an appointment to the Federal Board for Vocational Education. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 21 June 1917, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges a letter from Dabney regarding a Mr. [Andrew] Hawkins. Wilson will put the matter in the hands of the Secretary of the Navy and assures Dabney that the Secretary will have a big heart in the matter. Wilson says that he is sorry not to have seen Dabney. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 June 22, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes in regard to Andrew Hawkins. Wilson received a note from the Secretary of the Navy in which the Secretary confirmed Mr. Hawkins' discharge. Wilson writes that this ends the matter and he is sorry the fellow is "not what he ought to be, but probably a good riddance!" The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 August 13, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of the 9th. He is glad the Dabney has been "paying his respects" to the People's Council; it is for the most part a "bad and mischievous lot." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 September 21, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes regarding Mr. Strickling's letter. He will put it in the hands of the Secretary of War. Wilson was obliged to Dabney for sending him the "very pointed reply" to Dr. Eliot. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 December 10, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of December 7th. Wilson will "see what can be done about it." There is an autograph note in Dabney's hand stating that the letter refers to "my request" that the President ask the Italian Ambassador to allow Lieutenant Bruno Roselli to stay two weeks longer in the United States to deliver his speech to more universities.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1917 December 12, TLS 4 p. with envelope and enclosures (TLS 1 p. from Assistant Secretary of State William Phillips and TLS 2 p. from the Italian Ambassador.) (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson encloses a letter from William Phillips, Assistant Secretary of State. Phillips states he has contacted the Italian Ambassador and requested Lieutenant Roselli be allowed to remain in the United States for two additional weeks. The Ambassador reported that Roselli had been recalled not because he had offended Americans, but because Italy needed officers in light of the great numbers that had been killed. Phillips also states that the Ambassador would, in light of the request, extend Roselli's visit for two weeks, and has telegraphed permission to Roselli. The Italian Ambassador writes that he has already taken steps to arrange for Roselli's visit to be extended.
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1918 January 3, TLS 4 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that he is unable to appoint Mr. Rutledge to West Point. He will only appoint sons of Army officers since to do otherwise would "ruin" him. Wilson explains that officers have no "political residence" and cannot obtain appointments through their House or Senate members. The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1918 June 27, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that he has received a letter from the Secretary of War telling Wilson that Corporal Charles W. Strickling has been commissioned as a First Lieutenant and assigned to Camp Jackson, South Carolina. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1919 February 26, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for sending a letter from Professor Richard Henry Wilson. The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- William H. Taft to Richard Heath Dabney 1919 March 18, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Taft thanks Dabney for his letter of March 14 and states that he is unable to visit the University of Virginia "for my work is too heavy to take on other engagements, much as I would enjoy coming to your Jeffersonian center."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1920 November 1, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of October 28 and states that he "need not assure you of the pleasure with which I receive any message from you or of my profound appreciation of your continued trust and friendship." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1920 November 10, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for consulting "about the publication of the letters" and asks Dabney not to consent to publication. Wilson states that he has "all my life had a passion for privacy which I hope may be indulged in this case." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1922 December 7, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson, 2340 S Street N.W., Washington, D. C., to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson says that he must decline to sit for a portrait by Wight as he finds it "the most fatiguing of all preoccupations." Wilson states that he is "getting slowly well, and there is so much remaining to be done that I cannot afford any other course." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1922 December 29, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Wilson, 2340 S Street N.W., Washington to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of December 27 and says it came "as a peculiarly welcome birthday message." He thanks Dabney for his continued support and friendship and closes with best wishes for the New Year. The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."
- Edith Bolling Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 1926 October 21, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Mrs. Wilson, 2340 S Street N.W., Washington, D. C., to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Mrs. Wilson writes in response to Dabney's letter regarding his manuscript. She asks Dabney to send it to her so she can read it; she will then "take up the matter with my attorney, should there be any need for advice, and am sure you will understand that my effort is to safeguard you as well as myself from any embarrassments in the future." The typed closing reads "Very cordially yours," and the letter is signed "Edith Bolling Wilson."
- John Randolph Bolling to Richard Heath Dabney 1926 October 26, TLS 1 p. with envelope (Box 2)
  Boling, on Mrs. Wilson's stationery for 2340 S Street N.W., Washington, D.C., to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Bolling thanks Dabney for his letter of October 23 and says that Mrs. Wilson will read Dabney's article as soon as she can. The typed closing reads "Cordially yours," and the letter is signed "John Randolph Bolling."